Okay, we're going to go ahead and get
started here.
Um
Amber is out tonight, so I'm going to be
filling in for her.
Um so, call the meeting to order at 6:00
p.m.
And um
first order of business is a roll call.
Um so, Amber, she's out.
Gary?
>> Present.
>> David?
>> Here.
>> Um I'm here. Elizabeth?
>> Patrick Bustos?
>> Here.
>> Kelly?
>> Patrick Vaughn?
>> Here.
>> Chuck?
>> And Josephine?
>> Here.
>> Cool.
Um okay, um and then we'll just keep
moving on. Um approval of minutes. Um
did anybody get a chance to look through
the minutes that Aaron sent out last
week from our May meeting?
>> June.
>> June, sorry.
Anybody want to make a motion to approve
any changes?
>> Josh, I just read through that. Um and
my only comment would be I wonder if we
needed to document um on the motion that
was passed last meeting to dedicate up
to a certain amount for fountain repairs
on the airport fountain. Do we want to
put the specific amount in there? It
wasn't listed previously.
>> Okay. Aaron, is that something we could
I know the city has sort of made the
change to do less detailed minutes
um in favor of like just sort of linking
to the video. Is that a level of detail
we could add in there specifically for
that one motion?
>> Terry, we can add that in.
>> Okay.
Thanks, Aaron.
Any other comments?
Would anybody like to make a motion to
approve the minutes?
>> I move
>> Accept the motion.
>> I accept the minutes.
>> Sorry.
>> Okay. Patrick uh Von moved to
and um David seconded the motion. Okay.
Um any further discussion
on the minutes?
And all in favor?
>> I.
>> Any opposed?
Great. Thank you.
Um
Okay. Then we will keep moving on to
disclosures. Does anybody have any
disclosures, conflicts of interest, ex
parte communications, anything like that
that they would like to disclose?
Nothing. Okay.
Um then moving on to audience business.
Um do we have any comments from anybody
in the audience who'd like to address
the board? Feel free to step up to the
podium. Just press that little button on
the um mic there on the base so it's
green.
And um
welcome.
>> Evening. Um do you need like name,
address, anything? Okay. Uh Clint
Taylor, Indian Paintbrush Architecture.
Um address is 9704 Vera Lane, Cheyenne,
Wyoming.
Um here to talk about uh house at 3136
Thoms.
Um
we are applying for a well, applied for
a building permit to add a garage.
Um part of that we've got to do a little
bit of demolition and so that kicks us
to to your committee cuz we're in the uh
2023 expansion of the Capital North
Historic uh District. Um
the demo permit got held up in the
city's system and didn't get assigned to
somebody so we missed the agenda for
this this meeting. So we'll be on the
agenda next month.
But uh wanted to come uh before you guys
so that we didn't lose any time. We've
got everything that you guys need to to
make it a pretty simple agenda item for
you next month.
Um
the house was built in '29.
Um you can see the the former garage. Um
didn't need much of a garage in '29. Um
it's been added on to in the back and on
the side in '54.
Um that carport was afterwards enclosed
to be kind of like a garage. So we kind
of got an addition to an addition. Um
the roof is really cobbled up. Um
the the two additions have different
siding on them. The original garage is
is full brick.
So with the addition,
um
we're wanting to take those two little
additions off and expand the garage out
to be a a modern-day two-car garage.
Um keep the the brick walls on the the
north and the
uh or on the east and the south.
And then um push that out, match the
roof best we can.
Um on
Yeah, so this is from Pershing looking
south. You can kind of see how the roof
there on the right is kind of cobbled up
and
um
you know, we've got all sorts of roofs
there, some flues that are going to go
away.
So that the new roof will do a a hip
roof on the garage and keep it below the
the eve of the house so we're not taking
away from the house.
Um if you could swing around on Google
to um the thames to the front of the
house on the left there.
Um you know, it it's a craftsman house.
We want to to to honor that. That brick
chimney that you see there and the glass
block the glass blocks been replaced
with windows. That chimney isn't
original. Um
kind of looking at the brick on that. It
matches kind of, but it's um the
scoring's different and it's a slightly
different color and it doesn't have the
dark um dark brown band that's on the
the house itself. So we'll match that
brick, so we've only got two bricks
instead of three,
um but match the addition instead of the
the historic house and extend that to
the right um and then that roof, you
know, it's sagging because the the
roof's added on to it just added weight.
So we'll have to replace the roof, but
that kind of carport on the right would
go away and around on the back and and
just clean it up. I think um I think
it'll really add to the house and I do
have say these are older Google Street
um images before the the homeowners
bought it. So they've done a lot already
of fixing the landscape on it and the
fence and um
and really dressing it up. So now we
just want to do the garage and and do
that. So
but our intent is to to preserve the the
historic house, not take away from it,
not block the views of it.
Um keep a
um a the same low slope hip roof on the
garage um and just complement it as much
as possible.
So any questions for me or the
homeowner?
>> Yeah, thanks thanks for sharing with us.
I was wondering if do you have do we
have any like renderings of the
>> Um I just did
>> planning to do and afterwards or
anything? Just I was curious.
>> be the first page should have just kind
of some 3D images of of what it would
look like.
Um that bottom image you can kind of see
like a darker it doesn't show up real
well with uh um
the overhang
um coming around.
And then we'll preserve that south brick
wall that's original to the garage. Um
and then you know, just butt up to it
with an expansion joint and then uh a
complimentary brick but it's not an
exact match so you can still tell
historic and and new.
>> Um Charles and Aaron is there I just got
the letter in the mail today that this
will be talking about this further next
month, right? And will you be sending us
like a a packet in the mail like you've
done in the past?
>> Yeah, chair through you we will be
sending out an um a staff report um with
all of this information next agenda.
>> Okay. And so there there's no action or
anything we're we're we're doing
tonight.
>> Correct. Okay.
>> Uh then are yeah, any any questions um
from other board members? Patrick?
>> Yeah, I just have a a two real quick.
Does the demolition and the addition of
the of the two-car garage change the
footprint at all? I mean do you does it
is it
a lot
>> We're extending to the microphone to the
north.
Sorry, turn it off so we don't get
feedback.
Um we're extending to the north. Um you
know, I taken the carport off that I
think was 12 ft and we're um doing a
garage that's going to be 18 19 ft so
we're pushing closer towards Pershing
but we're keeping that roofline down low
and um you know, it's got fence all the
way around so I think it's you know,
it's going to be pretty well hidden and
not
you know, we're we're certainly not
sticking out closer towards Pershing
than than the adjacent homes or anything
there.
>> And do you know if the city allows that
footprint to extend this certain length
or are you familiar with
what that
>> I've been talking to Aaron about that
and and doing all the the stuff we need
on that on the the building permit side.
>> And and the second question I have is on
the
picture there's that white I don't know
if if I think it's a
a rolling fence.
That will be the front of the of the
two-car garage, correct?
From the street?
>> Um
>> From the front.
>> Go back to that.
Um yeah, that would be kind of your view
um coming from
um
Thoms there.
That you would see the the garage there.
And we're trying to keep it off to the
side from the house
um and not block the the gable ends of
of the house there.
>> Yeah, that that right there that white
>> Yeah, so that that would go away and
then we would have the garage door
there.
>> Garage door and that garage will
probably end up
like extending out this what out this
direction towards
>> Yep.
>> towards Is that That's Pershing or
Thoms?
>> Yeah, Pershing.
>> Pershing. Okay.
>> The the view is from Thoms.
>> Okay. And
>> And they're they're doing that kind of
the carriage style garage doors. Um you
know, kind of a a wood grain or
something so it's not
all that white there.
>> Okay.
Um And and then you mentioned the
chimney.
Um you're going to match You're not
taking it down or anything.
>> No, no. We'll we'll leave that, but that
brick is a a different brick than what
the house is.
Um the scratch is a little narrower and
it's deeper
um and the color's a little off. So
we'll we can match that brick. So then
um we'll match the addition instead of
the historic house.
So that you can still tell historic from
addition.
>> And I I I keep asking questions. I only
had two.
Um you would talked about all the
different sidings.
There were like several.
And and will that
kind of be what you're thinking of
trying to make it more
uniform or you know, that the addition
I understand will be different, right?
>> Right. Well, so in that picture, kind of
that shed roof on the left, um, I think
has aluminum siding on that. Or is that
the wood siding? Well, one's got
aluminum siding and then that other
addition has a a wood siding. Neither of
them really match the house. We'll take
that off and then the the entire garage
will be full height brick. The um,
everything will match and kind of keep
with the historic
theme of the neighborhood.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks, Patrick. Any other questions
from any other board members?
Elizabeth.
>> Um, you said that some
I'll say alterations have already been
made, but in terms of landscaping,
um,
cuz looking at the house from Pershing,
uh, it looks like the view will be a bit
different. So, is there kind of
landscaping going up? What
>> Um, just like in there, you see all
those weeds and and the grass, you know,
they've they've got sod in there, clean
that up. Um,
you know, just
got a lot more grass there and making
the yard a lot nicer.
>> Yeah, it just seems the view from
Pershing and Thoms will be a bit
different.
>> Um, from
from Pershing, it'll pretty much be the
same because that fence will still be
there. We'll just be a a little closer
to the fence and the roof will be a
little closer.
Um, from Thoms, we're we're just taking
some fence out and that carport and then
stretching that roof out a a bit more.
>> Yeah, I guess I was thinking more in
terms of the the feeling of the property
itself, but um,
fortunately, that's my drive home
tonight, so I can swing by and see what
it looks like.
>> Any other questions?
Okay, well, um thanks for for coming
tonight, and I think we'll we'll look
forward to talking with you again a
month from now um at the next board
meeting. Is it Charles, is there Aaron,
anything else we should
cover now?
>> And chair members of the board, just
wanted to note that what you all will be
reviewing technically is the demolition
of the historic element of the
structure, and the structure is unique
in that it has two different elements.
You have the original structure, which
dates back to the early 1900s, and then
the 1954
um addition. So, that's what you're
looking at, and then um number one is
appropriate for demolition, and then um
the reconstruction, you know, it can
can the addition, that is something we
can look at, but it's not the specific
application. So,
um when you're trying to link this all
together, um you can look at the
demolition and what the replacement
value is, essentially, and by value, I
mean the aesthetic value and
appropriateness to the original
structure.
>> Thanks, Charles. And yeah, hopefully,
you can sort of walk us through that uh
next month further, as well. So.
Okay, yeah, thank thanks for your time.
>> Thank you.
>> Um any other audience business? Is there
anybody online, Aaron?
>> No, there's none.
>> Okay.
Um then, we will move to um comments and
report from our city councilor
representative.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. Uh
missed the last couple meetings.
Once I was
uh at the announcement for
the PBR headquarters coming here and the
Hall of Fame.
Uh
and then I was in
Mexico on vacation
in June.
So, sorry I missed those ones. But but
it's been
pretty exciting and hectic at the
council
over the past couple months and [snorts]
uh
a lot of great things, you know, we
had our uh recognition of the committee
for the 250th celebration and I think
that went really well off with
a lot of
4th of July glory.
I know the mayor was worried that you
know, there wouldn't be very many people
come to the parade and it was
people were 15 deep all through that
route. It was
one of the largest parades I've ever
been part of.
Uh
we opened the
Belvoir Ranch to the public. 32 miles of
trails are now available.
I talked a little bit about that to some
of your colleagues when I first got
here.
Uh
that when someone made a comment that we
don't
cherish our western heritage anymore, I
said name another city that does it that
owns a ranch.
Uh
so, I don't know if there is. Maybe
maybe Charles knows, but
>> What? Harvey has a ranch?
>> I guess the next town over has one.
It's not as big as ours though, is it?
Okay.
We got a big ranch.
Uh
and then uh
the historic train cars were brought
down to the depot.
Uh
and also the the depot has a new
restaurant, the Rail Yard. I went in
there the other day.
Uh it's a unique menu. Uh they have a
$75
cheeseburger in there called the train
wreck.
I I don't know if that guy that used to
do Man vs. Food will come here for that.
Maybe.
Uh
they're unveiling the
the galloping
horse above the Wrangler. And do you
know what time that is tomorrow? It's
before
Reyes on the Plaza at 5:30, something
like that?
>> I do not know when and I'm just
pretending I don't know about
the nominee for
>> Oh, okay.
Maybe that's not historic preservation
then.
Uh
>> No, it's I don't know what time it
Then chair three, I don't know what time
it that is, but um
that's being organized by Pete Leybourn
and I can reach out to him real quick
and see if we can get a
some information from him.
>> Okay.
Uh
then the
the Morningstar Indian Village's grand
opening is Friday at 10:30.
Uh just driving by, you can tell it's an
amazing
uh
addition to Frontier Park.
Uh they moved some
of their bronze statues around and they
moved some of the
the parking lot is going to be very
different this year.
Uh
the addition of shoot nine also
uh looks amazing.
Uh
then uh
going back to our meeting that ended
this morning at 1:41 in the morning.
And that agenda, uh
and if you ever
heard of a little uh company named
Microsoft?
Well, anyways, they uh
bought some land from the Lamus Ranch.
Uh 3,500 acres. 500 of it will remain
agricultural, will be a
uh barrier
between the Sweetgrass subdivision and
the ridge that is to the south of that.
There'll be a conservation easement up
there.
Uh so, what I told some of the the
residents,
you know, that's probably the luckiest
subdivision in Cheyenne because you know
there's not going to be any development
now
behind you.
Uh there could have been a wind farm up
there on that ridge. It could have been
a
uh
solar
chemical plant.
What else did we turn down? Uh meat
processing plant.
Uh so, we don't just automatically take
every company that looks to come to
Cheyenne.
Anyways, uh
I think it's a a real big deal
for Cheyenne to have the opportunity now
to
have these type of jobs in in our
community.
And uh
I talked to one guy on our break and I
said, "Would you rather the data centers
leave Wyoming to your children?"
And I know that be an easy answer for
me.
So, when we went to tour it,
uh
it was
a lot different than what my vision was
before I went in.
I figured it'd be noisy and
uh
hot, right?
And it's it's just a
big brick [clears throat] building with
lots of security.
And and a lot of security, probably more
than Fort Knox.
But uh
the the fears, you know, and I talked to
the people that work there, said, "Why
are you not afraid of your
the health effects from the data
center?" And people that live a mile
away are.
And he said it's just fear.
It uh
uh
it's like a wildfire, I guess. It
spreads.
And uh they don't understand because
they're
they're not there and they're not
working in it.
But, uh, a lot of the workers we've
talked to said it's changed their lives.
And, uh, I think as legislators,
counselors,
that's our job is to
make life better for our constituents.
And, I know there's there's two sides to
that that issue.
Uh, but, uh,
up for the council on annexation, we
look at criteria that's set forth by the
legislature.
And
if the five [clears throat]
uh,
criteria's
meet the annexation, then it says we
shall annex.
Uh,
the other thing is a lot of the
tax incentives that the state
legislatures
implemented
is really what I think is added to
the data center boom in Cheyenne. So,
they have a
sales and use tax exemption, so they get
that on the servers,
processors,
a low sales tax and a low property tax,
no no state income tax, and no corporate
tax.
So, those five things
are what corporations like Microsoft
look at when they're looking to
uh, expand to a community or a state.
And, uh,
in my opinion, I'm happy they they chose
Cheyenne.
Uh, so, in in 10 years, maybe the
naysayers will look at it different.
Uh,
so,
are there any other questions about
annexation or
us being up
for till 1:41 in the morning?
No.
>> Thanks Representative Esquibel. You guys
have been busy.
Any questions from the board on any of
>> And I know we've been really busy.
There's probably a few things I missed.
>> I have a comment for Mr. Esquibel.
>> Yes, sir.
>> I made a field trip last week to the
Belvoir Ranch
and
I was first one in at 8:30. So I hiked
several of the trails
and just want to thank you and your
group for making that happen.
Just the whole layout, the way the
trails were marked, the parking area,
everything set up to go.
And so I was just very impressed that uh
the work that was done out there.
And I could kind of see where there some
further expansion will take place. So
you know, there's a covered picnic area
and so forth.
So
I just want to thank you for that.
>> And the guy that helped us with that,
Tim Thibodeau.
Was it Tim?
Um
Tom Thibodeau. He helped with uh
Youth Conservation Corps.
>> Todd.
>> Todd. Thank you.
And uh
doing the Curt Gowdy State Park trail
system over there, too.
And
my first year in the legislature, I went
over there and spent the night with the
kids and helped build those trails. It's
It's hard work.
And I I couldn't do it now.
So
I was a lot like younger back then.
Uh but
uh it's
I told my wife we need to go get her a
mountain bike. I have one, but uh
uh
hopefully we'll get out there and be
able to enjoy it, too. And then again,
we also did a
member this um appreciation uh for us
Councilman Scott Roybal. That was his
passion.
Uh and there's a brick or big rock out
there that has a
a bronze plaque in it to uh
recognize Scott.
Close friend of mine, too.
>> Any other questions or comments for
Representative Esquibel?
Okay, thank you. And we'll move on to uh
comments from the Planning and
Development folks.
>> Good morning, chair members of the
board. Uh Charles Bloom Plaine, the
Planning Director. I just wanted to note
one thing real quick that kind of is uh
related to the data center stuff. Um one
of the items
uh one of the reasons we like to see the
data centers are we get a heck of a lot
of property tax revenue from these
facilities. Um in 2012, um our assessed
value of all of the square footage of
buildings and structures that we had in
the city of Cheyenne,
that was 511
million, 900,000 approximately.
So, that's, you know, just a half
billion, roughly. In uh 2018, that
number had increased to about 660
million dollars.
Um just in 20 uh 25, that number has
surpassed 1 billion dollars. So, it's 1
billion 93 million dollars in valuation.
So, that's the assessed value of all the
properties that we base our eight
collection off of for our general fund.
How does that translate into additional
revenue for the city? Well, that dollar
amount that we received in 2012 was just
over 4 million dollars that would go to
our general fund to support items like
preservation initiatives, uh parks and
recreation, planning, the mayor's
office, the council, all of that type of
stuff. So, that was 4 million dollars
back in 2012. Now we're sitting at 8.7
million. So, we've over doubled that
dollar amount just based on the
investment community, which is not just
data centers, but it's also new
apartments, new housing, those items.
So, we're continuing continuing to see
that grow, and we are on the edge of um
possibly having
uh possibly another billion dollars of
investment that's just sitting here
knocking on our doorstep. So, that's a
lot of additional funding that could be
coming our way um with this development.
Um and with the data center uh
discussion, that's just a piece of the
puzzle. Uh we do receive sales tax
revenue off the electricity that's sold.
We have revenue through our franchise
agreement um and such, which that
increases our our um general fund as
well. I believe in 2018
um our general fund was sitting right
around $55 million.
Um
um and that's your non-enterprise um
items, like not trash, not water, not
that stuff. Um now we're sitting at
right around $80 million. So, we've
really seen an increase in general fund
revenue, which can pay for a lot of
these quality of life improvements and
maintenance of our roads and removal of
potholes and such, which seem to be the
trending issues when elections come up.
Especially mayoral elections, it's all
about potholes.
Um so, that's just just a little bit of
information on how we we've changed um
and how we have um our own different
type of coal that's knocking on our
door, which could lead to uh development
in the area, but we have to be
responsive.
Um and we have to plan and and do
everything smartly. Can't just rubber
stamp everything.
Um something that we are are doing is we
are continuing forward with our
comprehensive plan update. We had a
selection committee that was um put
together. That selection committee
included a member of the planning
commission, Tony Laird, Jeff White, uh
council representative from Ward 1. Uh
we also had Steve Bourne, he's a local
developer. Uh we had Justin Arnold from
the county planning office, a handful of
planners in the office including Aaron,
myself, Connor White, um and
Seth Lloyd, but he was on
he was on vacation, so he didn't get a
select. Um and then we had a engineering
representative and also represent from
the MPO. Well, we had narrowed down
um what turned out to be eight qualified
um
um consultants and we have made a
selection and we're entering into
contract negotiations.
Um the selected firm that we're
negotiating contracts with is House
Household um Levine. They're a
Chicago-based firm that's done a lot of
national
um comprehensive plans. Um they're going
to tackle some of the top um items and
issues here in the community like data
centers, but they'll also be tasked with
looking at um
principles that we aspire to regarding
historic preservation. So, as we move
forward with uh putting together a
steering committee, I would uh really
appreciate if there's anyone that has
some additional time that would like to
wear historic preservation hat on that
steering committee a more even uh some
type of hat in between that's historic
preservation and maybe more downtown uh
design standards or urban design
standards type of hat to really look at
how we want to shape our community
because what we're planning for and
designing now, that all has the
potential to become a historic building
in the future.
Um we're anticipating to have that uh
professional services agreement approved
um on August 24th and ready to sort of
kick it off in early September.
Right now, it's uh
envisioned to be an 18-month process.
There may be some pressures for us to
look at expediting that process. Um
we'll just see how how quickly that
could be.
So, stay tuned. Keep that in your hip
pocket as as an opportunity for
um
before um additional participation.
Um other items we have in our department
is we are uh continuing to be
tremendously busy with different items.
Uh lots of challenging public hearings.
Uh challenging developments that are
going through the public process that
are keeping us up all hours of the
night, which is good. It's entertaining.
I'm never a dull day in the planning and
development office.
I'm lucky for the governing body. It
looks like we may have some reprieve
from longer meetings for just a couple
of meetings before it just revs right up
again.
So, but there are some other large
developments that aren't
just data center related. There's true
uh
industrial development that's proposed
that's coming down the pipe. Um there's
additional um multi-family development
that's going
going forward.
And one item that the governing body
approved last night um is kind of the
second part
of a partnership with
um a
uh
an LLC. It's a It's a multi-family
development group that's constructing um
essentially workforce housing at the
corner of Carlson and Converse. This is
the northwest corner
um of that area. If you've driven that
area, you've noticed that there's a
large area of land north of the existing
apartment complexes that has been graded
and and has um earth moving on it. Um
this is a partnership between the city
and that developer to create housing
that is uh envisioned to be at a a point
that 60% of AMI for income. The AMI is
the um area median income. So, what is
60% AMI? These are some of your uh
people that are entry-level positions in
the school district, you know, your
teachers, some of your folks that are at
at hospitals and stuff. Um it's referred
to as affordable housing you know, at
the national level, but affordable
housing unfortunately has taken on a a
bad
uh bad taste. Everyone just thinks
affordable housing means
bad housing. But it's housing that all
of us probably have needed at some time
in our life.
Um and I like to remind everyone that
even though apartments are being built,
just because it's an apartment complex
doesn't make them a bad person. I mean,
I guess I kicked all my bad habits when
I moved out of my apartments, right?
So, we've had staff members that have
been in apartments as well.
So, um that's that's a exciting
development that's uh moving forward.
Um also in our department, um we
continue to um
navigate
um
what is envisioned as we need to take
care of this now type of scenarios. Um
one of those is continuing to move
forward with
what we're calling our farm-to-bus um
ordinance bundle. This is a group of
everything related to urban gardening,
urban farming,
uh farm stand sales from
from pickup trucks and trailers and and
food stands. That was first discussed um
in conjunction with our last and final
county pocket annexation that kind of
ran across a bump and got postponed
until November.
Uh we are in the final um stages of
assembling a variety of pieces of that
puzzle internally and looking to get
that out um for public comment. It's
going to uh revolve around everything
from
from food sales to
gardening at your house and how it
relates to state statute and also
includes uh provisions for um how
livestock and grazing can occur on
larger acreages that may not be zoned
agricultural, but may be a holding zone
for future large-scale development or
leasing opportunities uh for grazing on
some of these underutilized industrial
properties that might be uh flood plains
or reservoir areas and stuff like that.
So, that's exciting. Um also we're
continue to move forward with uh
discussion on trying to uh
navigate what um
if any changes may be necessary
regarding large
uh
large caliber industrial development
like data centers and other ones. Um
whether we look at uh community benefit
agreements annexation agreements and
those types of items as they come in. Um
it's been discussed a lot at the the
governing body level. Um there has have
been internal discussions as to how we
can can handle that and how we can
handle it for future developments at the
time of site plan instead of having it
done necessarily annexation.
So, um another item that is kind of uh
hot topic at the
city level um is our engineering
department is working on a redesign of
the Yellowstone and Dell Range
intersection. This is the one um
essentially
at the end of Dell Range at the end of
the runway where you can go straight and
you can get into the golf course um or
you can turn left and follow the road
and and go around the golf course to get
to I-25.
Um there's a proposal to uh redo um that
intersection to prioritize uh turning
movements that might link the southern
extension that goes towards central um
to link it more as a thoroughfare to
uh Dell Range as it heads towards the
shopping center and maybe have a like a
a flip where you have to turn to get
onto Yellowstone. Um there's some uh
discussion on how that relates to
um the current um bicycle network as
that's one of our original Cheyenne
bikeways and seeing if that can be
preserved because we don't want to take
steps backwards in in uh uh active
transportation. So, that's uh not
a good uh
way forward as active transportation
continues to skyrocket, especially use
in the city. As you might notice, a lot
more bikes and alternative active
transportation modes clogging our
greenways, sidewalks, and roadways.
Um in addition, we have an intern in our
office. Uh he is evaluating the current
uh bicycle
uh route that is on 22nd Street, which
does traverse several of our historic
districts. Uh right now it is
haphazardly signed from 20
12 roughly with a couple of this is a
bike route sign between Pioneer and
Logan.
You might see that on that street. Um
he's working um
in conjunction with our active
transportation advisory committee, which
meets on the third Monday of the month,
to look at what it would take to
formalize that into what would be a
MUTCD and uh NACHTO. Those are the
acronyms for transportation um compliant
bicycle way. That would be um
identifying uh signers that would note
on-street bike lanes. It would also
um
clear clearly mark them throughout the
corridor and possibly introduce those
fun bicycle
arrow symbols that designate shared
lanes for sharrows. So, that would be uh
pretty cool and um helping formalize a a
non um heavy traffic
uh roadway vehicular-wise um to
highlight that for bicycle
uh
tourism or bicycle community or just
bicycle riding because that is going
through one of the the heart of some of
our historic districts. And
if you ever take a chance to bike or
walk down that street, you'll notice
that the environment um changes
throughout and it actually has some
pretty good um history and character in
that area.
Other than that, Aaron, am I missing
anything
big on here? I
Uh
uh we
we have been working on the landscape
ordinance, the revisions to our
landscape code, uh with Councilmember
Rinne,
um for way too long. I want to say about
2 years, it seems like we've been
walking through this with a couple of
breaks here and there. I'm going to try
to work on this time allows.
We are anticipating
to have a final landscaping ordinance
draft um available for public uh comment
and possibly just moving straight
towards adoption um in the next couple
of weeks.
So, we're going to move forward with
that.
Um that should address some of the
uh shortfalls of our current
landscaping. Um it also uh tries to make
it a little bit easier to understand. Um
and I believe it's addressing some of
our uh more problematic provisions we've
seen
uh regarding uh like outdoor storage um
areas, which have been challenging to
administer. Um and also um just aligning
with some some best practices and
specifically allowing for water-wise
landscaping.
And the final thing is I don't know if I
mentioned this. Uh
recently we uh approved amendments to
our development code regarding what's
commonly known as historic horse racing.
Uh that was approved at a recent
meeting. We just updated our development
code that now reflects all of those
changes. Essentially, what it has
created are
uh receiving zones. They're called
overlay districts, where we're
encouraging those new uses to occur. One
of those areas is the High Plains uh
interchange on South I-25 by the Welcome
Center, and there's an existing facility
there.
Um
three other areas include West Lincoln
Way within the city limits. This is
essentially from Crow Creek to the west.
These are properties adjacent. So, it's
more of a regional
anchor to try to attract people from out
of town. And then two other areas in the
community are 15th Street corridor and
the Reed rail corridor where they would
be allowed in that area. With the Reed
rail, it would be set up in a way that
they would have to be adjacent to the
corridor and they would have to take a
principal access like pedestrian access
off of the corridor unless it was not
possible. So, for example, if one of the
properties was adjacent to the rail
corridor and they couldn't access it
because there's a service road there,
they could then go off the street.
The final thing I'd be remiss if I
didn't mention this is
the 15th Street rail exhibit had three
rail cars that were installed uh
over the
on Monday. It was last last Monday, I
believe, is when they were installed. Um
that is phase one of that. Uh so, feel
free to go check it out. Right now, you
can still check it out and you can
check it out as close as you want
because the fences have not been
installed. I'm not condoning anything.
But, I did hear that it's a little bit
of a free-for-all over there and some
people may have been able to go into
some of those cars. So, I'm not saying
you should, just saying that as that's
I've heard, but you can get a good look
at those. Um there's a video that the
DDA has put together as well um that
uh documents the move and how they um
unloaded them and put them together.
It's actually quite an exciting project
and there's a lot of work that was put
into it.
And that's an economic uh development um
administration um project, so that is
uh that has about 10 years of reporting
that our finance department's going to
have to do um in regard to identifying
how uh that resulted in job creation for
new businesses that would be attracted
to the downtown area. It's not a simple
relocation. It would be new businesses
or expansion of additional employees
that would have occurred because of that
item.
So, that's all the updates that I have.
>> Thanks, Charles. That's a lot. Yeah, you
guys got a lot going on.
Um I have a couple follow-up questions.
Um you're talking about the the master
planning process um and how you're
looking to have some sort of historic
preservation representative
um involved in that.
Um
could you let me know if I sort of am
understanding this right that you're
you'll put together a committee as soon
as you get the um
sort of the contract with the consultant
finalized and things going and you'd
you're interested in maybe somebody from
the board serving on that committee to
sort of speak for historic preservation
through that process. Is that right?
>> Two or three of the members of the
board, yes. And it'd be regarding
historic preservation and also an urban
design type development.
Yeah.
>> Yeah, I think I think that that'd be
really important for somebody on the
board to be involved in that. So, I
don't know if there's any interest from
anybody on the board right away, but um
if there is, yeah, I would encourage you
to speak up and maybe, you know,
figure out how to how to get involved in
that. Do you think that'll start in the
next couple months?
>> Two or three of the members of the
board, as
as this the definition of what the
process looks like evolves,
um I will make sure we get that
information out to you. Um
right now the consultants are at a S3,
which is a GIS user conference, graphic
information systems. Um so, we're
planning on getting the scope finalized
uh by the next by the 31st of this
month.
Um and then during that scope
refinement, we will have identified how
many stakeholder meetings and steering
committee meetings there will be. So,
we'll get that done. They will primarily
be
on uh line, we believe. They'll be on
like a Teams style call.
That's how I believe the most effective
use of our budget and time would be.
But, there will be some elements that
will be in person. We just don't have
those pinpointed yet.
>> Uh yeah, thanks. But, if you could just
keep us updated on that, it would be
great to have somebody there.
Um
this is maybe a a bigger question than
we want to get into, but you know,
you're talking about the community
benefit agreements with um industry and
and new um development coming in. And I
know there's been discussions about
whether, you know, levels of
appropriateness for for that type of
thing. But, I wonder if there's been any
conversations around
how we could tie in historic
preservation to that type of
community
benefit agreements with with industry.
Like, I
yeah, I I don't know.
>> Uh chair three to the board, I think
that's a great idea. And also, I I would
like to note that even if someone is on
the steering committee with a historic
preservation
hat on or urban form type of hat on, it
doesn't um restrict them from talking
about other policies like the Land Use
Plan
um any other types of things that may be
there. I'm not going to
to mandate that anyone just say, "This
is your lane. You have to stay in it."
You're You're there because that's the
lane you can travel in, but you're
welcome to add a person hop in that
carpool lane. You bring up a really good
point. Um I do know that um I think uh
Well, Meta has a community action
grants, and I think Microsoft has some
other grants as well.
Um
I believe this, after talking with some
of those representatives, I believe that
uh
seeking
grants from them is something that's
possible. But this community benefit
agreement type of piece
um I think
we could explore how we can work
historic preservation in there. There
are some limits that our attorney is is
looking at as to where we can balance
that.
>> Cool, thank you. Yeah, I mean I think I
think it could be really beneficial for
for historic preservation if you want to
keep looking into that. Um I have one
more comment and then I'll go over here
to Gary, but um
not related to anything you've
mentioned, but I'm just curious
um what's going on with the Hines these
days cuz you
sort of talked about it um a few months
ago um and sort of talked about maybe
um sharing some more information with us
or
putting together a tour or something and
I'm just curious if there's
where things are at with that project.
>> We don't know.
>> No, we haven't heard anything from the
Hines. I will uh we can reach out to the
owner's rep and get a tour scheduled.
That That's slipped my mind.
>> Cool, thanks.
Um
Gary.
>> Well, I'm all for growth and making
Cheyenne bigger,
but
what came to mind was as as we sit here
at this board, our main [clears throat]
focus should be historic preservation.
Um and I'm going to call up uh ordinance
I saw put together in Deadwood
that after they put gambling together,
they made an ordinance to put aside and
it was a little bit. I mean, it was a
1/10 of 1% goes to historic
preservation. That was their budget.
With that, they have orchestrated a
museum with over 3 million pieces of
artifact. Now, sometimes that's just a
piece of barbed wire they dug out 16 ft
from where Wild Bill Hickok was shot.
But, they've got money and they're doing
good with it. As opposed to what we sit
with here, and I'm just talking about my
last 12 years of experience, sometimes I
can't even get a plaque for a historic
preservation award because somebody said
they ain't damn tight with the money.
If the money's out there, we ought to
have a percentage of it
given to this board to manage because
I'm telling you
um and most of you should know this,
it's not easy to generate money.
We've kind of come into a little bit of
a windfall with some things we do, but
before that, we couldn't we couldn't buy
paper.
And um now we've got some money, but I
know how city government works, you're
going to spend every penny we give you
or you collect from revenue, and then
this group has to fight back to get
to get it. I mean, look at the pump
house. We've talked about that for 4
years, there's no funding, no funding.
Um
I guess it's a a big order, but it'd be
nice if we could
take the gambling money from
a percentage of the gambling money from
the horse tracks, call it what you want,
it's a gambling casino. Um you've got
this big windfall now in the data
centers, big taxes, a percentage of that
should go to the historic preservation
of Cheyenne, Wyoming because if it
doesn't,
it's not going to be here and you're
going to be sitting here on a board in
10 years going,
"Geez, we need another $85 to go buy a
sign to put up over at uh the depot and
six councilmen don't want to give it to
us." It'd It'd be really nice if
somebody could work as and I know it's a
big job and I don't even know if you
could get it through, but it would be
great if a certain percentage of that
money went to historic preservation and
I
I I think the public would probably
support that.
Um even the people that don't support
it, so um, just a thought to put in your
mind, but uh,
it's an opportunity and once you miss
it,
it's over.
So, thank you.
>> Okay, Patrick.
>> I I have a a a question for Charles.
Charles, you mentioned landscaping
guideline.
Um, one of the things that come kind of
comes to my mind as it turns of
landscaping,
um,
I don't know what the guidelines say
now, but is there any
contemplation
of looking at landscaping from historic
preservation standpoint?
One of the things and I don't know if in
the landscaping guidelines, there's any
notion of fences and you know, how
fences
I don't know if they're considered part
of landscaping or part of of of of
building and how
fences
um, I've been in some really interesting
discussions about fence height and fence
width and and materials on fences,
but they do have a real impact on
historic preservation, especially
streetscape.
That's really important in terms of
if able to look down the street and see
the streetscape as opposed to fences
that that kind of obscure that that that
that feeling in the streetscape. So,
it it may be a a down in the weeds kind
of question, Charles, but I've I've I've
seen it before
in a in a negative way,
but I'm wondering if that's a
consideration in in terms of the
landscaping guidelines, just a question.
>> Uh, Chairwoman of the board to board
member Bustos, that's a really good
comment and we do have regulations
regarding fences and we did do a an
amendment uh recently. it's about what
say is that 3 to 4 years ago.
Um the quick answer is the fencing is
its own standalone section not included
in landscaping. However, uh
in some
aspects of larger commercial or large
residential development, there are
opportunities to provide ornamental or
decorative fences that can substitute
like trees and bushes and stuff like
that. Those
those you're going to find in a lot of
your newer developments and anything
that could be a large uh redevelopment.
I believe when the um
VOA um did their demolition and rebuild,
I think they had an alternative. Did
they put in a Did they put a decorative
fence in a portion of that?
I think there was a
No.
Okay. The I thought there was a possibly
a discussion about using that as an
alternative at one time.
Um but regarding fencing, our
regulations are are fairly simple,
um which restrict it to uh 4 ft in the
front yards, and there's a certain
material standards which are like wood
um
uh painted wood uh wood
there's uh like iron, those types of
fences.
Uh but there are prohibitions on some of
your non-standard materials.
Um we don't have a standard that creates
uniformity.
Um I
often times point to staff uh a little
OCD concern with
fencing just looking up here on uh 22nd
Street. If you look between O'Neal and
Thoms, if you ever look at that whole
block there,
everybody has a fence in their front
yard, and everybody's fence is
different. But they're all 4 ft tall.
You have chain link, you have wood
pickets, you have white vinyl, you have
white pickets, you have it's
everything's different. Um but that's
kind of the way that our fencing
ordinance has been is
that everyone can choose their own.
From a preservation standpoint,
the only area where we're able to review
um a fence and the design is in that
Governor's Mansion overlay, which is
that capital
um the overlay district where
we have um I thought that would have
been our
neighborhood resident by chance where
we have that um property that
the owner may be here for discussion
today or may not.
Um but those are ones where any
structure, even a fence, can be reviewed
for appropriateness with the
neighborhood.
Um but those are items that can be goals
and and items we can look at with
preserving our heritage and and such in
the comprehensive plan.
>> Um
would it be advisable, Charles, or even
feasible to to
in the landscape guidelines to at least
um
for maybe like um North Capital
you know,
uh
historic district, maybe
the Southside historic district, make a
a recommendation that we at least
consider a historic
uh
and not not mandate anything. I
That's not what I'm looking for. I'm
looking for maybe some
you know, at least consideration in
terms of when looking at landscaping to
at least give some credence to like
historic preservation and and it
it's I'm trying to explain what a what a
what a lands what a a streetscape at a
and and a community feels like and it it
it's hard to to put that into words,
Charles, and I guess that's what I'm
looking for is is there any way to say,
you know,
in the landscape guidelines at least
consider, you know, streetscape and
community feel.
Um
and maybe it's not even feasible, but
that that that that's where I I I feel
like, you know, we
we lose the the character, I think, a
lot of
in neighborhoods if if if if we don't at
least consider the historical context
and landscape of the community.
>> Chair 3 to Chris board member Bustos, I
completely understand
your concern and my OCD example is a
great example of of things.
Um
two things. Number one, our fencing
standards
um regarding materials are
for things that require the the permits
and such like that. The
um standards,
a lot of them are more reflective to
Sorry, I'm going to back up. Our
landscaping standards
generally don't apply to single-family
developments.
Um the fencing standards do, but a lot
of times um
fencing enforcement
and guidance is only provided if
someone is kind enough to inquire about
a fencing standard.
Um and then enforcement occurs if a
neighbor is unhappy enough to complain
about their neighbor.
We get lots of fencing comments.
Um
so it it would be um challenging, I
think, for us to put in recommendations
and ordinance. I think a more proactive
approach that might be better
would be some type of informational
uh brochure or something that we could
have on our website that could
be um additional info with our fencing
guidelines saying, "If you're in a
historic district, here are some things
that you should consider. Um here are
some takeaways."
And it's not just how does it relate to
a property aesthetically, we also uh try
to advise people on fencing in
commercial standards because we look at
at safety and stuff. For example, we
want to try to prevent large fences from
being put up adjacent to alleys. I look
at that car dealership on Ames and uh
Lincoln Way right by the pump house.
They wanted to put up a large fence and
we said, "No."
Because sometimes when you put up a
large fence in certain areas, you create
avenues for bad activity to occur.
Um so that could be something
that we could look at as a as a board,
maybe as a side committee where there
could be a best practices manual put
together.
I could uh reach out to the University
of Colorado, which every year they offer
us um
essentially an in uh uh
a graduate student um
that can put together specific projects
and that might be something that would
be right up one of their alleys cuz
historic preservation is a pretty key
element in the architecture and planning
program at the University of Colorado
Denver.
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> Any other questions for planning
department?
Okay. Um we're going to move on then to
uh strategic goals report. Um first up
is
uh National Register of Historic Places.
Um Elizabeth, do you have update on how
um your two projects are going?
>> Yes, it is crunch time cuz we got 2
months essentially um to get these done.
So, I don't have very long updates, but
it's been a lot of work going on at
least. Um for the African-American
context study,
um been looking at census records
comparing them back to Sanborn maps and
Polk directories as well to find um
obviously not resi- just residences of
uh folks in town, but also associated
businesses and things like that, too.
Um
one thing that I'm running into is that
in the contract, there's no date of
significance for it. So, um my intent
was to go back 50 years, so 76.
Um one thing that's tricky with that is
that census records cannot be released.
There's a 72-year restriction, so that
would be the 1950s.
Um there are some local contacts that I
can speak to as well, um but I don't
know if that's a concern
uh of privacy that we want to have for
the board. Um obviously from a
preservation standpoint, 50 years is
golden. Um
but that is something to consider as
well. And like I said, there is no
actual set date of how far um forward
we wanted to go with that. So, I don't
know if
anybody has thoughts, ideas on that, if
I s-
do the best I can um uh or if people
feel really strongly about the date.
>> I mean, I don't I don't know. My sense
is that you're the contractor and we're
paying you just for your expertise in
figuring out the the best way to handle
um these situations, so
I I think like, you know, whatever you
feel like is the the most appropriate
way to handle that in terms of the
period of significance.
Um
and maybe it's Yeah, I don't know.
>> I mean, is there any way like you could
reach out to the SHPO and the state SHPO
or someone else who I'm sure there's
somebody else has run into this problem.
Maybe uh
I I don't know another city uh
something.
>> Yeah, I know I know they've done a
statewide
um
uh con- similar context study as well.
Um
so yeah, I guess duh, I should have just
referred that to see what they did, too.
Um but I also want to be respectful of
folks, too, who might want that kind of
privacy. So, um yeah, like I said, it
wasn't mentioned in the contract, so I
just wanted to double-check to see if
there was intent of period of
significance for that. So, I will move
forward as I see fit, unless somebody
>> We've never We've never had a
conversation as a board about the period
of significance.
>> Cool.
>> Um so that's that guy. And then um the
other one, obviously, is the terminal.
Um I've reached out to the city public
records office um due to scheduling um
with the fourth and I'm going out of
town and they were going out of town,
what what have you. Um hopefully I'm
getting in there by the end of this
month to start going through the
historic records that the city has um as
well. Uh I've also contacted the state
library and the county library, too, to
get in touch, but I haven't heard back
from either of them. So, um I can also
start poking people that know through
other contacts to get in there, as well.
So, that's that.
>> Charles, did you have a comment?
>> Uh through you to uh board member
De Granier?
Incorrect. De Granier, just making sure
I'm pronouncing it correctly.
Um, who was your contact regarding the
historic records? Was it someone in
building or was it the clerk's office?
If you don't recall, that's fine. And
microphone.
>> I think it was the clerk.
>> Okay, cool.
>> Yeah.
Correct way to go.
That's who I've been chatting with.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Um, thanks Elizabeth for the
update. Sounds like you've
still got a ways to go before the next
couple of months, but um, yeah, reach
out if if you need anything.
Um,
okay, um, moving along, the strategic
strategic goals report, oral histories
project. Um, I again this month don't
have any updates. Um, I was on
uh, vacation and before that, um,
very busy with the 250th events for
work. So, I don't have any updates on
this unless Patrick
Bustos does.
>> I have just a slight slight update. Um,
I was out at the
community police department community
night out and I ran into a gentleman
with the Winooski Independent Citizens
Coalition, uh, Palmer True Hill, and
he's agreed that he's real interested in
working with us on that particular
project. So, um, it was just fortuitous
that we were at the same event and we
kind of hooked up and so he's real
interested in
assisting us with this particular with
contacts.
>> Right.
>> Gary.
>> Um, just out of curiosity, how many oral
histories has the board completed?
Five.
>> And we welcome all the help we can get
from anybody else who wants to do oral
histories with us.
Um okay, uh moving on, historic
preservation month, um that was in May.
Um the note on here, the DuBois Award is
reopened to July 31st. Aaron, do you
know have we got any submissions at all?
>> Oh, last time I checked with um Matt
Murphy, we hadn't had any, but it's been
a while, so I'll need to check with him
again.
>> Okay.
>> And Tara, I mentioned at the last
meeting that I thought I had known
someone who had done some renovations
uh to a home that were historically
appropriate. I reached out to that
person, they said
they apologized that they
they hadn't used exact materials on it,
so it wouldn't be qualifying at for the
discussion.
Um and that person, I don't want to
identify.
They were embarrassed, but they said, "I
know we couldn't afford it."
>> Um
Yeah, so it's open through July 31st, so
I I feel like at the next board meeting,
hopefully maybe you'll have a couple
that have been submitted to present to
us. Um I feel like
we should probably um
also be as a board over the next month
thinking about any nominations that we
want to make um in the case that we
don't get any um submissions.
So, I would propose that everybody
think about that um
and and come to the next board meeting
with with any ideas if you have any.
Josephine?
>> Well, I think we should have at least
one cuz I had someone reach out to me as
a former
recipient about how it works, about one
of my neighbors. And so, I I kind of
walked them through filling that out, so
I think they should have that.
Um
so there's at least one.
>> Great. Nice. Okay, so hopefully we have
at least one and hopefully um
board members can think about some
possibilities over the next month as
well.
Um I don't know who is the chair of the
historic preservation month committee.
Does anybody know?
Are there any other updates from this
committee?
It might be Amber who's out.
Yeah.
Okay, um
then we will move to education of the
public in historic
preservation/marketing
committee.
>> And one one thing I have is
kind of covers ornaments. Like Gary and
I are going to
we've got a table set up for this
aviation thing that's coming up at the
airport so we can sell ornaments again.
Uh but in the past we had a pamphlet
that we would hand out and that I
thought we should redo that but Amber
said not on her watch. So
is there any way we can get like a QR
code thing that says if you're
interested in what's
worth preserving in Cheyenne
have that thing on there so they can
click on it to get to our website so
that we can
you know, get people that are going by
cuz there's going to be quite a few
people there and if we get a few hits or
whatever we can but I don't know any
other way to uh
get people to to our websites other you
know, just having them randomly hit
our web Facebook or whatever page isn't
done seem to be working super great but
uh I don't know how else how those QR
code things work but it'd be nice to
have something we could stick
up there.
>> Do you want like a a half-page flyer
something with a QR code that you
>> Well, I'd like to have a Disney site.
I'd like to kind of have a just a piece
of cardboard kind of that we could stick
up on the desk there so that they can
click on it when they're
walking by.
>> Okay, does anybody know about QR codes
or how to do that?
Any?
>> Let me Let me back up. What What's the
problem with printing a page besides
Amber doesn't like it?
>> Well, I just that's a planning thing. I
brought it up and she said no and nobody
else would have
went with it. So,
I got shut down. So.
And
the next thing I have I ran into
Christine Bromer who is the St. Mary's
teacher that was doing the third grade
class for the historic buildings and she
has gotten a better offer from Classic
Academy and will no longer be teaching
over there, but she's going to be in
fifth grade at Classical Academy. So,
that won't be one of her topics there.
So, I'm going to have to get with the
St. Mary's. She said she left all of her
teaching materials there at St. Mary's.
So, if the new teacher wants to teach
it, she's got the thing already set up,
but it's going to be up to the new
teacher.
But, she said she would also
help me
with the
talking with Classical Academy to seeing
if they could do something for their
third grade class there as part of it
since she's familiar with it. I'm going
to be teaching over there.
So.
And
that's all for now.
>> Elizabeth, do you have any comments
about like the social media or anything?
>> Yeah, so I know I was approved to spend
some money to boost the um award
online. So, I'll do that um as well.
Uh historic wise when I was checking my
stuff, there's nothing too
exciting happening. Um but of course,
Cheyenne was founded on August 7th. So.
Um I will go ahead and post something
for that. Um there also was the um UP
survey at the end of this month to Um
what was that 1867.
So I'll I'll put some stuff up for that
and I know railroad goes over very well.
So we'll do that. There's also
possibility to put up some CFD
images to of downtown showing off some
of the historic buildings as well. So
I will get all of that scheduled.
Unless I'm missing anything that anybody
else wants.
>> That just does good.
I found the core of engineers reports on
the flooding in Cheyenne but I forgot
left it at home but it seems it was the
1896 flood wasn't too big a deal cuz
it's like about four lines but there was
another one I think in 1906 then it's
almost two entire pages cuz apparently
the town had built up a lot more over
those
10 years or so. So but the other
interesting thing is
they have the dates of all the big flood
events on both Dry Creek and Crow Creek.
So you can
go back to the I don't know how much has
been digitized of the newspaper articles
health you know but if with those dates
that it makes it easier to find the uh
the you're cross reference to the actual
information. So but I will get those
to you.
I just kind of been sitting in the same
spot for last months.
Yeah.
>> Thanks Elizabeth. I all those the
pictures you've been posting over the
last couple months I feel like they're
get a lot of traction on social media.
It seems like people people like that.
So
Um ornaments Gary.
>> Well there's a lot going on with
ornaments and I want to make it brief
cuz I don't want you to run a meeting
into 1:30 in the morning like the city
council.
Um I have ordered and they're on the way
and that would be the two ornaments. I
have one of the capital I redid for the
capital museum exclusively
to sell. I've also done the train depot
and I'm getting I have those, but I've
got to print the brochure for inside and
I'm going to use those strictly down at
the depot. The reason I'm doing that is
because my ornament that I'm selling to
everybody
is not going to appeal to the tourist in
my mind. They like capitals and
trains and
the new ornament is finished. It's in
production. It is of the two water
towers north town.
And I have contacted the guy that's
painting it. He's going to give me a
little bit of paint.
Which costs $470 a gallon.
I'm going to put a dab of that paint on
the back of each one of those ornaments.
And I'm only ordering 600 of them this
year because the governor usually buys
150 from me and I'm doing an exclusive
with them.
So,
I guess my question would be to
planning, are you going to sell them?
The ones I don't sell, are you going to
sell them out of planning like you did
last year?
>> Through with the board member Sims, yes,
we'll go ahead and
>> And and that's good because we found
that when we start you know, we're
finding checks in the bottom of drawers
that are year and a half old when we let
other people do it and
it'll be nice that you can do that and
I'll probably give you some ornaments
of the depot and the capital that you
can pedal also. The exciting thing was
is I met with the governor and his wife
about doing their ornament, which is
their last year in office. So, they want
to give everybody something to do. So,
just um
part of what I'm going to do
is I'm going to have the flag in the
background, the Wyoming flag.
Then I'm going to have the capital in
the front.
And then I'm going to have him and her
in the front waving goodbye from the
steps. And then while we were doing
this, their chocolate labs ran by. They
run wild at the governor's mansion. So,
they get to be in the ornament, too, the
two chocolate labs, and they're thrilled
with that. I guess I haven't seen
the total of what I'm doing with that
finished yet. But, it's really getting
too busy. They wanted her seal on it for
hunger initiative. They called me
yesterday and wanted the boot on there
that's they're putting in the the cowboy
boot with the hunger initiative. And
then, he wants his seal in there.
Um and then, hardly leaves me any room
to put my little hidden stuff in, but um
it's it's going to be exciting, and um
we're going to generate some money from
that one. And of course, I'm giving that
all to you guys, too. So,
that's all I've got.
When uh
uh
>> I have a picture of this year's if you
want to look at it. I sent it to a few
of you, but
Yeah, this airport uh thing is also an
opportunity for us to try and get rid of
some of those uh airport fountain that
we had to a bunch of those left over
that we found that Kathy found at her
place. So, with it being right by the
airport there, hopefully we can get rid
of some of those.
Yeah.
>> And Gary, we did receive uh
an invoice for your ornaments, and we
did process that through our department.
So, there was an invoice that came
through for the depot. Correct.
>> Thank you. That's all I have.
>> Well, thanks as always, Gary, for all
your work on the ornaments. Yeah.
>> It's fun once it
You guys know how that is. Once you see
the end product, it's really fun what
it's worked out to. It's
>> Sure. It's fun after all the work is
done. Yeah.
>> Sure. And actually
>> re- remind everyone, I believe this is
board member Sims' last year doing the
ornaments?
Okay, so just for succession planning,
remember
you someone will need to pick his mind.
The ornament part.
No, but they should pick his mind if
they would like to to follow uh suit
with that in the connection. So, it's
very
people look for this every year. In
fact, this actually settles my Christmas
list for like about six people every
year.
>> That's what I talked about earlier.
If you aren't selling ornaments, you
don't have any money.
You have none.
So, you need to follow up, and I'll be
glad to do that, and I'd probably even
do it on the side for you if
push came to shove.
Okay.
Thanks, Gay.
Um airport fountain planning, Kelly, any
updates?
>> Um just a little bit. I don't have a
whole lot of new new updates, I guess,
but kind of as a recap since our last
meeting when we approved up to $25,000
um for some necessary fountain repairs.
So, some of the main items we were
hoping to get quotes on or tackle with
that initial sum of money were um first
to replace the plumbing that's causing
the city issues and clogging the filter
and fried their pump and all of that
last year.
Um
I did talk with Jason Sanchez. He said
he went out for a couple multiple
plumbing quotes on that, and he has
gotten some feedback. One of the
plumbers he's talking to had a good
suggestion, it sounded like, to replace
that with copper piping and stainless
steel nozzles that they think will hold
up better long-term.
Um
second, we wanted to um remove some of
the failing grout and the missing grout
and just replace that around the base of
the exterior of the fountain where there
might be some storm water seeping in.
Um so, I have a message in to one of the
masons here locally,
as well as trying to clarify with
Pacific Coast Conservation what the
requirements are for that because they
had noted in the report it needs to be
conservation grade grout and um I can't
remember when they were here. I think
Lucinda mentioned something about
it might even be restricted to certain
like
conservation specialist that can order
the material. So, I'm trying to clarify
with them what we would need to do
specifically if we're going to bring a
local mason to do that.
Um
We talked about potentially getting a a
fountain or a water feature specialist
to look at it just to verify um the
waterproofing is intact and because
there's some visible cracking and stuff
in the in the basins. So, um haven't
reached anyone on that yet, but I do
have a message into Sawyer Waterscaping
to see if that's something that they
would look at for us.
Um Jason Sanchez also said he would talk
to a specialist because one of the other
items in the report I can't remember if
I mentioned this previously
was that Pacific Coast Conservation
recommended rather than treating the
fountain with chlorine which can be
corrosive to the terracotta it's
it would be better to put it in some
sort of UV filtration system.
Or if they need to treat it with
chemicals, I think she said bromine is
less corrosive. So, I did mention that
that to Jason. He said he would discuss
with a specialist and see what their
thoughts are.
Um
See.
And then they had mentioned maybe
installing some mesh screens or bags or
something at drain locations to prevent
you know, leaves or dirt or whatever is
getting in there from clogging the
filter.
Um but Jason did say he doesn't think
that's the issue. It was more just the
corroded plumbing piping that's rusting
and and going down into their system and
clogging that up. So, um then the last
thing was just to replace the broken
glass panes at the light at the top of
the fountain. Jason said he would work
on that as well. So, it is helpful. um
He was willing to tackle several of
those items and basically just said if
our team would focus on trying to find a
mason.
And the one that he didn't specifically
address was the water feature specialist
for waterproofing. So, I've
at least started reaching out on that
one as well to see if we can get a
couple people interested and give us
their opinions and quotes on
any necessary repairs. So,
Jason did say I just ran into him a
couple days ago. He has been talking to
plumbers. He didn't say when expecting
to get those quotes, but on the
filtration system, he said it would
likely be August. Everyone's been super
busy
with Super Day and Frontier Days and
everything leading up to that. So,
>> Thanks, Kelly. So, it sounds like stuff
is sort of moving forward.
And hope It sounds like it was helpful
that we sort of approved some money for
Jason to make those repairs at the last
board meeting. And we're sort of at this
point just waiting for for those things
to sort of
get followed through on.
>> Yes, for sure. He did say that was
helpful and will help expedite their
process. So, once they do get
a quote that they're happy with, they
can go ahead and
get that going as soon as possible. And
hopefully, like we had talked about last
month, get a plumber on board before the
end of the summer and before the end of
the good weather so we can at least
address that and hopefully fill the
fountain for a short amount of time
and see how
it functions and how the terracotta
repairs fare, I guess, with it being
filled at least for some amount of time.
>> Good.
Is there anything you need from the
board on that or any like action we need
to take this month to get things moving
forward?
>> I don't think so, no. Once we have some
some quotes on those items. Um
as long as it stays within the 25,000, I
think we'll
we basically were approved last month,
right, to make a decision to to move
forward with those items.
If it does exceed or if we have any
questions or anything, hopefully by next
meeting we would have an update on that.
>> Cool.
Thanks, Kelly.
Um
pump house.
Are there any updates from the city on
what's going on with the pump house?
>> Chair members of the board, we don't
have any updates. Um I'm surprised.
There was
some information, I believe, that was
secured, but that has not been shared
with us. We've asked for it, so we
haven't seen that yet.
>> But there's there's information like
from the architects that got in there or
what
>> Uh chair members of the board, it is my
understanding that they had a firm that
came in and they did a structural they
started their structural evaluation of
the building, and they're working on
finalizing the report. Um I had asked to
to see if that was complete. I don't
believe it's
been completed yet. I think it's close.
We'll let you know as soon as we find
out more. Um the
what I understand is
there's a belief, after talking to
people in an unofficial capacity, that
um it may not be any different in price
to rebuild what's there right now um
versus the restoration because instead
of having to
utilize and find matching materials that
that are exact or deal with the exact
structural elements, they can rebuild
and um mimic with essentially the same
way something that would um visually be
the same, but be structurally different.
So,
um that's the unofficial word I've
heard, um but I
won't believe that until I see the final
document.
>> And you're referring to the roof
specific Is the roof
>> the materials on the roof because
they'll just be
But hopefully they would at least start
be trying to get close, right? Chair,
shape of the roof and everything.
>> Chair, yes, we're watching that. There
would be opportunity for salvage of the
tiles that are there, the terracotta is
terracotta tiles I believe on the roof.
Is it terracotta?
Or what type
>> It's like a tin or some sort of metal.
>> Is it metal?
>> Mhm.
>> Gosh.
It's like you got me all confused.
Um anyway,
there would be opportunity for some
salvage of some of those materials and
preserving the design. So, I don't have
too much more of an update on that.
But we have there's a lot of watchdogs
on that.
Kelly, did you have a comment?
>> I do, yeah. I have a little bit of an
additional update because
that
initial phase of that project of
restoring the roof structure and
re-roofing it is out for
um CMAR proposals right now.
And I was at the um pre-proposal meeting
on site the other day. So, they're
trying to get a construction manager on
board
to essentially demo
the roof structure
and then put new roof trusses on and
re-roof it
by the end of this year, it sounded
like.
And then move forward with future phases
of
restoration and rebuilding the interior.
>> So, that would lead me to think that the
report has already been completed.
If they're if they're already putting
stuff out to bid, right? So, is there
any way to get that information from
what the
architects found?
>> There's a way. I will ask again.
And when once we get that information,
we'll get it your direction.
So, we we've requested a couple times
from different folks and I don't know if
it's
um getting lost in the shuffle, but
we'll see if we can get that.
>> Any other specific questions or comments
from anybody on the pump house?
Okay. Well, we appreciate you keeping an
eye on it and
trying to track down that information,
Kelly.
>> I think they did mention while we were
there that the there's still some
investigation going on. So, I don't know
if, you know, the report is finalized or
they're just trying to get
a CM on board proactively, I guess, to
before they finish the design and put it
out to get some input on like what the
best way is to demo the roof
and put it back together.
Is my understanding.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, cuz we couldn't go into the
building. They said there's ongoing
investigation and
but
>> Okay. Well, we'll look forward to
hearing more information about the pump
house.
Um, moving on, design guidelines. Amber,
um,
has sort of been the one um, leading
this effort. Um, and she's not here
tonight. I haven't heard um, anything
recently about the design guidelines. I
don't know
if anybody else in the committee has.
Yeah. Um, but I feel like it's it's
something we need to start moving on
again. So, maybe I'll reach out to
her and um, see what she has to say. And
do you have comment about the about the
design guidelines?
>> Hi, um, Sophia Mezdrik, executive
director. Um, wanted to let everybody
know that Cass Rafa was on this. She's
no longer with the DDA. Um, she
uh, has handed it up back to me and um,
just anyway I can support. I've I've
forwarded Amber a couple of the drafts
that we've had like from the '90s or
early 2000s. I don't know how useful
they are. Um, but yeah, let me know if
you'd like any assistance or support in
that effort.
>> Well, thanks, Sophia. Yeah, I got the
email from Cass when when she is
leaving. Um
but yeah, I think it's uh I'll
reach out to Amber and see if uh what
our next steps should be on this.
Um watch list items, does anybody have
any comments on any of the watch list
items?
Okay, we're going to move on to new
business. Is there any new business from
anybody?
Patrick.
>> I'm
I don't even know if I don't even know
if I should even bring this up, but um
maybe Gary and David could speak more
clearly clearly to this.
We seem to show up sometimes at at
different events or have tables. Do we
have like any like
banner or anything like that or a a nice
table cloth that identifies us as the
historic preservation board? Is that
something that this board has an
appetite for to
kind of maybe draw people in or at least
have a professional image when we're
out at different events?
>> I think there was at one time.
I don't know where it disappeared.
>> And Charles, is that common for a board
to to to do that or
is that like frowned upon? I'm just I'm
just curious because um
you know, uh
sometimes just seeing a banner will draw
people in and and and you know, I I we
have a little bit of money and I don't
suspect it'd cost a lot to
you know, get something that says
Cheyenne Historic Preservation Board and
>> [clears throat]
>> Chair through you to board member
Bustos, two things. Number one, um I
vaguely recall a banner and I vaguely
recall seeing one around the office.
And emailed um the past
planner that was here, Lonnie,
um to ask him if he recalls a banner.
Secondly, if we don't have one, we have
a specific line item for public meetings
that we can use, which we use for
engagement efforts. So,
I'd be happy to fund that banner from
that line item. So, we could get that um
we could definitely do that. We could
also use a tablecloth that we could
interchange for different ones because
presently we borrow from
the DDA.
They're so generous.
But, yes, we we can definitely do that.
We're we're in the process of
investigating right now like that.
>> So, I would suggest we assign that to
somebody and get it made.
So, you could do it, Charles. And
like what is it was one of those
stand-up things and then maybe a
tablecloth that says I don't know what
what
options are. I don't really don't. I
mean, I I used to do this at my previous
job but 30 years ago and we had a
pull-up banner and you know, a nice
tablecloth that had the our um
logo on it and it it just I know, it
just I think it draws people in and it
makes us look a little more
professional.
>> Terra 3 distributes Crayola and poster
board. Um no, those are all common items
that we can look into. I just
the one thing I needed to understand is
what will our design ultimately look at
look like.
Um
if we have some ideas of what we want to
put on there, we could probably work
with a vendor like uh PBR. They they do
graphics and design.
I don't know if Trophy Creative does
that as well. They might.
>> There's a there's a sign company down on
20th that
>> In the sign company?
So, and then the other uh folks in the
city have done that. I believe the DDA
recently
did something like that. You have one of
those banners, right?
I think it came from the 20th Street
folks as well.
PBR, we just need to double check to
make sure we have a good design
element. So I don't know if you wanted
to have
If anyone feels graphically talented
enough to put together
a design that's more than an ornament,
but
I'm just kidding.
Gary has some experience. No, I'm just
kidding.
>> I'm thinking let's keep it simple.
Cheyenne Historic Preservation Board.
Make it blue and get it done. And if
you'll fund it, I'll go get it made, but
I don't think we need to put graphics on
it or get all creative or tie it up for
another 3 months off and on.
Give me the go ahead and I'll get it
done.
And our last one was with Don. We had
one.
And he had it with my ornaments last
time. He
>> So Don might may possibly still have our
last one.
>> He gave me a box of stuff and it wasn't
in
>> And that was a banner that would strap
under a table, I believe. That's what it
was.
>> Because he's absolutely right. If you're
sitting there, you look like two street
people walking in and sitting down and
looking for somebody to talk to.
>> Okay, well, I feel comfortable with
Gary,
you know, sort of
figuring out what the design looks like
and and I agree keep it simple. I
And before
>> $8,000.
>> Before Gary jumps in on on that, I want
to double check with our
I hate to double check, but with our
PIO, we have some branding our public
information officer. We have some
branding standards we're supposed to
follow or we get our hands slapped. Um
this comes out really good time because
right now we
we realized that we were we were trying
to get the branding put together for the
planning and development department and
a pop-up tent that would go as well.
But, we ended up postponing that last
year because we're waiting for our new
branding to come out. And then when it
came out, we all forgot that we never
ordered it. So, when we started setting
up for Super Day, we're like, "Oh, crap.
We forgot to order this."
Um so, I think we can take care of it
all, but I think we can go with a
simplicity mode um that Gary has
mentioned. Doesn't need to be anything
fancy.
Um so, we can we can do that.
>> Yeah. This uh things that August 15th
and 16th if we can get it for this year.
>> I don't I'd have to double-check time. I
don't think it'll be that problematic to
do.
>> Come on. Thanks, Charles, for
taking care of that for us. Appreciate
it. Um any other new business?
Charles?
>> Uh chair, this is the is this the last
item on the agenda?
>> Well, we have old business with David
Palacio, and I don't know is he present?
>> He's not present. He did end up showing
up to the last meeting after the meeting
ended, but
and I don't know if he's going to be
here tonight, but yeah.
He did come to the last meeting, but the
it was over. It was when we were
cleaning up.
>> Okay.
>> But, we told him we would have it on
today and we sent him the agenda and but
>> Okay. How should we move forward with
with this?
>> just have to
I guess remind him a few times again and
hopefully he comes to the next one.
>> Okay. And he
>> And also send a violation notice or
something an update regarding that
process to compel him to understand the
need to be here and provide the updates.
>> Okay. Cuz he's are we are
are we supposed to be approving
something from him or is he supposed to
just be updating us on the process of
that project or what's the What are we
trying to
What are we waiting on from him?
>> Uh chair members of the board, I believe
what was supposed to happen there is he
was supposed to provide periodic updates
as the status of the project as part of
our approval. And at that point he's
lacking in that. So that would be
failure to comply with the conditions of
approval. Um so the last item he had
mentioned is he's replaced the chimney.
And the term would say in form only, not
really a material as if you've seen it.
Because it's a cinder block chimney
chimney. Um but we'd look for a little
bit more of an update from him. So we
can escalate that to to get the
seriousness going.
>> Yeah, I think we probably should. So.
>> And um the one other item I have is
Sorry.
>> Before we move off of that item, can I
ask a question?
Um and
again, I don't know if this is
appropriate, but we've been messing
around with this for a long time.
And Charles, there is no
time limit, right? I mean it's it's I
mean it's
We finally got the bulldozer moved.
But I've been on this board for 3 and
1/2 years and
I, you know, with exception of the
chimney, I haven't seen a lot of
progress.
Um so I mean, are there any options for
us to kind of move this along or, you
know,
put any stipulations on
Cuz we already gave him the approval,
right? And we can't go back and
retroactively say, "Hey, man, you know,
um
got to have some kind of progress."
Just a question.
>> Uh chair, through There was a point
where the building department and the
inspectors there were working with him
and they were going to give him
deadlines and timelines of when he
needed to get some things completed.
There's been a also a lot of change over
in the building department now, and so
it's probably something we also need to
speak with them about and see if they
can get that timeline going again.
>> And Chair and members of the board, does
everyone know what property we're
talking about? I know we have a couple
new folks.
>> Yes, because I occasionally get like
newbies to Cheyenne wanting to live in
the historic district. Well, what's
going on with that property? Somebody
just need to buy it and fix it. I'm
like, well, that's a story I don't have
time for.
So, I don't if in this capacity know
kind of formally anything that's gone on
just visually
answering for Cheyenne, like I don't
actually know what's going on with that
right now, but I know somebody's trying
to
keep it and allegedly
restore it. So.
>> So, you will report back to us what the
building department says.
Cuz that seems to be a common thread is
when we have a big change over and
things get dropped and
pretty soon it's not an issue again
until something catches on fire. So.
>> Charles, do you want to give like a
high-level overview for Josephine or or
some of the other newer board members?
>> Uh Chair, yes. A high-level overview of
this item is um one day uh Lonnie,
myself, and Josh went to Cincinnati for
a historic preservation conference.
And at that conference we became
energized and said, "Hey, we have a
local ordinance district where it
requires uh board um historic
preservation board review for all
changes." Um we were like, "Let's come
back and let's really work on promoting
this for the historic district." Well,
unbeknownst to us, while we were gone,
uh the owner of the land uh the
property, started a renovation without
any building without any true building
permits other than a small interior
remodel and managed to take out uh
several key walls and support structures
for this building. Um didn't follow any
historic district type of standards or
any of the the regulations or processes.
The only thing he had ever done prior to
this was
he had come to the preservation board
and said, "Hey, I'm thinking about doing
a renovation."
Um and the board said, "Okay, well, work
with us to go through the process to
make sure you're doing a renovation in
compliance with
um our standards, which really are very
broad and open for the Governor's
Mansion historic area. It really is
is the modification of the structure or
the construction um compatible with the
period and time of other structures in
the district. It's very very broad.
There's no design guidelines.
Um after the renovation
and the remodel started, we red tagged
the property, which is a stop work order
from the building department, had some
inspections with with him, and worked
with um
him to
get it back to a structural soundness
level. Um it was
um
he hired uh a local engineer, structural
or architectural engineer, I believe
that was his title. It was a Deacon
Maggard, um to help um identify how they
could support the the house and get it
back up to snuff. So, those minimum
improvements had been made to stabilize
the structure, but since that time we've
had some compliance issues with
him uh changing the scope of work and
modifying the exterior of the building
in ways that weren't satisfactory to the
um
to the preservation board.
There was a time between
his uh
enhancements to the property without
permits or that outside the scope of the
permit um and uh
his most recent work where he did come
to the historic preservation board and
he uh sought approval and was given
an approval. I don't I don't have that
in front of me today but part one of the
elements I understand was that he had to
report back as to what updates were
going on.
Um I don't know the status of where it
is right now. Uh we'll need to check
with the building department to see if
they have an active building permit
still.
>> Oh, I want to take you back further than
that because 6 years ago
I was walking down the street and he was
out there pulling out rotten timber out
from underneath that house and that's
when I came to you guys and said,
"What's going on over here?"
And the building department says, "We
have absolutely have no record of him
requesting anything." At that time he
had a front end or what do you call one
of those giant
tractors? I mean, it's one made to move
huge boulders and he had that there and
that was broken down and it sat there
for
>> Mhm.
>> 4 years.
And uh but he didn't he didn't initially
get a permit. He we actually contacted
him because we were watching what's
going on over there.
So.
And then he came in and asked for
permission to get a variance on the
front porch that he'd already put on and
we didn't give that to him because it
wasn't compatible with the rest of the
uh the neighborhood. However, we did
make the stipulation that if you keep
the front
of the building looking like the
neighborhood, we'll basically kind of
ignore the back of
and so he responded with that by
building a metal shed in the back
that was two stories high and we had to
put an end to that. So,
I'll be anxious to see
>> And the the biggest issue with this item
is that, you know, it has had uh zoning
enforcement through the city attorney's
office.
Um their biggest struggle with
enforcement is the bandwidth to push
this through the process.
Um and that's
where it is right now is in in immediate
it's in the middle of a of an
enforcement process and
I do not know that
desire to move forward with uh like a
final enforcement action.
They have talked with our city attorney
now because that too has changed since
the initial
>> On a little side note, his main
motivation was to get bedrooms built
over there for his children. I'm sure
they're all graduated by now.
>> I I do remember doing a tour with with
him of the structure and he indicated he
was putting in I believe it was bedrooms
for each of his children. I asked him
how old they were and I suggested he cut
down the bedrooms because at least two
of them would be grown adults by the
time he was done.
>> Thanks for that sort of uh
uh overview of of uh what that process
has been like and yeah, I think if
there's
a way to uh let him know that we we
certainly need to start receiving those
updates. I think um yeah, that would be
good.
Um
Okay, um
other business, I the only thing I
wanted to mention is that I know um this
is Josephine's first time being here in
person. Um she was on the call a couple
months ago. Um so, she sort of met us
virtually, but I don't know if
Josephine, you just wanted to introduce
yourself to the rest of the board and
say hello.
>> Yeah, so I don't I'm not sure how much
you guys want to know. Um I my
day work is with the Wyoming Coalition
Against Domestic Violence and Sexual
Assault and their policy and systems
coordinator. So, I love policies and
ordinances and all kinds of things that
enforce those and if they're bad, I love
to change them. Um, we got to follow
them in the meantime, right?
So, that's my day job. Um,
interestingly, I've been discussing with
the coalition about like
historic preservation and downtown
development things like that, especially
as it relates to housing and um, you
know, modern upgrades that that enhance
the
safety of the community. Um, reducing
opportunities
to create victims like in parking lots
regarding like what lighting looks like.
So, all stuff they never thought about
before and I sit around and think about
for no particular reason.
So, that's kind of a cool crossover um,
we're we're looking at right now
how to
be useful in those spaces. Um,
I've
twin toddlers. They've called me 14
times since I've been here cuz they
figured out how to use an iPad. So,
um,
but yeah, she's Cheyenne native and I'm
really excited for this opportunity.
>> And many of you may remember that
Josephine received the Do Boys Award
from us last year for her work
preserving her house on 22nd
turn 19th.
>> 19th and we're buying the house next
door. Um, so
>> And you're going to work on
>> Pray for me.
>> preservation there, too, yeah.
>> It's a mess.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, yeah. It's it's fabulous. It's
huge. It's um, a giant project.
>> Well, thank you for joining us and
welcome.
Um, Charles, did you have something
else?
>> Yes, uh, chair members of the board. Um,
we do have one vacancy still on the
preservation board
and we did receive an application and
Holly Martinez, she's the executive
assistant to the mayor who manages
boards and you all have talked to her
sometime
or seek reappointment through her. She
had forwarded over an application we
received from a person who's interested
in serving on the board. They did apply
uh shortly after Josephine had applied
and they actually sent a recent inquiry
asking for the status. So that it's more
than just a one-off, let me do it. They
actually have an interest in it. Um I'll
real quickly just walk through this
person uh for you.
Um the person's name is uh Steven
Hanlin. I don't know if anyone knows
this person. Um he is a Cheyenne
resident, lives up in
um I believe that's up in Thomas
Heights, up in that area. He describes
himself as uh one born and raised in
Cheyenne and a member of the county and
state historical societies. He has a
long interest in Cheyenne history and
particularly in observation of all
Cheyenne structures and buildings. Um he
states, "I would enjoy participating
discussions about the resolution,
potential preservation of history and
buildings with local history.
I would hope to contribute via
solicitation of expert opinions and
application of my reading on local
history, application of my interest in
architecture, and application of my
woodworking knowledge, and application
of my engineering background." That's a
lot of that does it.
Um overall, he states he's continuously
looking for opportunities to participate
as a member of the Cheyenne Board or
Council um and assist the community
which has been integral to his
development. He feels strongly that
items and buildings with attached
stories of our history should be
preserved if possible, but through
rigorous process providing understanding
of inputs, pros, cons, costs, and fund
sources.
Um he's considered applying to this
board in the past but felt at those
times he was unable to commit the time.
Now he believes he has um the time and
he still has continued interest. He
looks forward to this opportunity with
the board.
Um he has some other volunteer
um experience, uh one being the
Technology and advisory council for the
city that was uh I believe Mayor Ward
started that. I'm trying to have a smart
cities initiative.
I can't comment on
how that initiative ended up. Um
Um I mean a lot of the There was a lot
of uh It was interesting because that
was about bringing broadband, but it
seemed like the private sector, you
know, they came and stepped in and
provided that that broadband. That's
pretty interesting.
He uh is a U-Dub venture mentor service,
and he's also uh volunteered with the L
Bogan Elbogen 50K mentoring, whatever
that is. Um
he has a career in medical product
development. Uh director of the
University of Wyoming bioscience
initiative hub.
Uh
pitch contest judge and mentor I-Corps
program faculty lead and instructor. Uh
woodwork with a fully equipped shop.
Maybe he could do wooden ornaments.
Uh so um anyway, he has a resume here.
Um I guess really I mean
we can go ahead and get this person on
the agenda for appointment at an
upcoming council meeting, and then he
could join us at the August meeting.
Um is this the person that you all would
like to see on the board?
I guess I sent out the resume and stuff.
Just looking for a feedback um as if you
feel that's that's good.
>> What do you all think based off of what
Charles just read
>> to us? Any comments? Thoughts? Does
anybody know him?
>> And typically we don't read this. We
didn't do this for you, Josephine. Uh
but we you know, this is a person that
had come in. We just wanted to run it by
the board because
I believe per the bylaws we're actually
supposed to run
um some of the candidates through the
the board.
Are we?
No, I thought No, that's a different
board. Sorry, that's the
>> Years ago
>> the board would review all the
applications and make recommendation to
the mayor, so.
>> So, we just wanted to have some more
participation with the board on
appointees. I think I personally think
they seem like an okay fit. But, I just
wasn't sharing this with you all of
you all saw any problems or
>> Sounds like a great candidate and we
could always use an extra person on the
board.
>> Yeah. I would
>> I heard a lot of mentorship in there,
which
tells me he might be
patient with things not moving quickly,
like a
six-year
project with a
bulldozer. So, not somebody impatient
and um
tempestuous with projects would be
might be helpful.
>> Charles, do you need a resolution from
the board or motion or anything like
that?
>> Uh Jim, as a board, no. I just look at
for just
any type of
if there's anyone against it or for it,
I'll just relay to the mayor what are
what's the general consensus that So,
>> I think the follow I think the fact that
he's following up on it is a good sign,
too.
>> That's what I thought was impressive, as
well.
No red flags?
No bulldozers in front yards?
>> Okay, any other
other business from anybody? We're here
at the end.
Okay, then um
with that, I'm will adjourn the meeting.
>> Should I adjourn the meeting?